<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Brendan King - projects</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/projects.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2019-11-24T17:49:00-08:00</updated><entry><title>Explorations in Deep Learning for Recipe Generation</title><link href="/recipe-generation.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-11-24T17:49:00-08:00</published><updated>2019-11-24T17:49:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Brendan King</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-11-24:/recipe-generation.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In my final two quarters as a University of Washington undergraduate, I completed a research project exploring deep learning approaches for recipe generation: a supervised learning task in which a model generates instructions for preparing a dish given a title and list of ingredients.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In my final two quarters as a University of Washington undergraduate, I completed a research project exploring deep learning approaches for recipe generation: a supervised learning task in which a model generates instructions for preparing a dish given a title and list of ingredients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will be adding some highlights here as I finish building this website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A copy of my final report as submitted is available &lt;a href="pdf/recipe-generation.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="projects"></category><category term="nlp"></category></entry><entry><title>Probannopy: probabilistic annotation and gap-filling of metabolic reconstructions.</title><link href="/probannopy.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-11-23T17:49:00-08:00</published><updated>2019-11-23T17:49:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Brendan King</name></author><id>tag:None,2019-11-23:/probannopy.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We provide an open source implementation of Probabilistic Annotation, an algorithm designed in the Hood-Price Lab at the Institute for Systems Biology.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We provide an open source implementation of Probabilistic Annotation, an algorithm designed in the Hood-Price Lab at the Institute for Systems Biology. This was published as an application note in &lt;em&gt;Bioinformatics&lt;/em&gt; in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Abstract&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gap-filling is a necessary step to produce quality genome-scale metabolic reconstructions capable of flux-balance simulation. Most available gap-filling tools use an organism-agnostic approach, where reactions are selected from a database to fill gaps without consideration of the target organism. Conversely, our likelihood based gap-filling with probabilistic annotations selects candidate reactions based on a likelihood score derived specifically from the target organism’s genome. Here, we present two new implementations of probabilistic annotation and likelihood based gap-filling: a web service called ProbAnnoWeb, and a standalone python package called ProbAnnoPy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://academic.oup.com/bioinformatics/article/34/9/1594/4756096"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Full Text Available Here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/PriceLab/probannopy"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Code and Installation Instructions Here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Why Probabilistic Annotation &amp;amp; Gap-Filling?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This figure motivates a simple use-case for our package in metabolic model gap-filling:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ProbAnnopy Figure 1" src="images/probanno_figure.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likelihood based gap-filling: (a) Gap in the metabolic network, preventing production of E; (b) A parsimonious gap-filling solution using two new reactions; (c) A likelihood based gap-filling solution using three new reactions, which are together more likely than the parsimonious solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Probabilistic Annotation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our work supports implementations for the algorithms described in this work:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Benedict MN, Mundy MB, Henry CS, Chia N, Price ND (2014) Likelihood-Based Gene Annotations for Gap Filling and Quality Assessment in Genome-Scale Metabolic Models. PLoS Comput Biol 10(10): e1003882. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003882&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Abstract&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Genome-scale metabolic models provide a powerful means to harness information from genomes to deepen biological insights. With exponentially increasing sequencing capacity, there is an enormous need for automated reconstruction techniques that can provide more accurate models in a short time frame. Current methods for automated metabolic network reconstruction rely on gene and reaction annotations to build draft metabolic networks and algorithms to fill gaps in these networks. However, automated reconstruction is hampered by database inconsistencies, incorrect annotations, and gap filling largely without considering genomic information. Here we develop an approach for applying genomic information to predict alternative functions for genes and estimate their likelihoods from sequence homology. We show that computed likelihood values were significantly higher for annotations found in manually curated metabolic networks than those that were not. We then apply these alternative functional predictions to estimate reaction likelihoods, which are used in a new gap filling approach called likelihood-based gap filling to predict more genomically consistent solutions. To validate the likelihood-based gap filling approach, we applied it to models where essential pathways were removed, finding that likelihood-based gap filling identified more biologically relevant solutions than parsimony-based gap filling approaches. We also demonstrate that models gap filled using likelihood-based gap filling provide greater coverage and genomic consistency with metabolic gene functions compared to parsimony-based approaches. Interestingly, despite these findings, we found that likelihoods did not significantly affect consistency of gap filled models with Biolog and knockout lethality data. This indicates that the phenotype data alone cannot necessarily be used to discriminate between alternative solutions for gap filling and therefore, that the use of other information is necessary to obtain a more accurate network. All described workflows are implemented as part of the DOE Systems Biology Knowledgebase (KBase) and are publicly available via API or command-line web interface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://journals.plos.org/ploscompbiol/article?id=10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003882"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Full Text Available Here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: KBase no longer supports Probabilistic Annotation as it was originally written in the above work, motivating our work implementing this as a stand-alone python package.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="projects"></category><category term="compbio"></category><category term="bioinformatics"></category><category term="cobra"></category><category term="isb"></category></entry></feed>